Contact

jdavis@ecri.org

www.linkedin.com/in/james-davis-msn-rn-cic-hem-ccrn-k-fapic-5b635863 (LinkedIn) www.ecri.org (Company)

Top Skills

Public Health
Healthcare Information Technology
Clinical Research

James Davis MSN, RN, CIC, HEM, CCRN-K, FAPIC

Sr. Infection Prevention Analyst, ECRI Greater Philadelphia Area

Summary

Mr. Davis is board-certified in infection control and epidemiology (CIC), is an APIC Fellow (FAPIC), holds national certification in adult critical care nursing (CCRN-K) and is a certified healthcare environmental manager (HEM). He received his diploma from the Dixon school of nursing, Abington Memorial Hospital in Pennsylvania and a BSN from Immaculata University in Pennsylvania. In 2013 he recieved an MSN in nursing education from Gwynedd-Mercy College. He is currently a Senior Infection Prevention Analyst for ECRI. He is a member of the Association for Professionals in Infection Control and Prevention (APIC) and has served as President of the Delaware Valley Chapter. He received Abington Memorial Hospital's Ignaz Semmelweiss Award in 2007 for his efforts in reducing central line associated bloodstream infection. In 2009 he was awarded an Innovator's Circle grant for his research in radio frequency identification (RFID) technology for monitoring of compliance with best practices related to infection control. In 2014 Mr. Davis was invited to serve on APIC national's research committee, and currently holds the chair position. Mr. Davis designed version 2 of the Pennsylvania Patient Safety Authority's state wide long-term care healthcare acquired infection reporting system and analytics programs. He has provided educational programs on infection control topics for risk management groups and patient safety organizations, as well as for hospitals, long term care and ambulatory surgery systems. He has authored multiple infection prevention and control articles and is published in the Pennsylvania Patient Safety Authority Advisory and the American Journal of Infection Control.

Experience

ECRI

Sr. Infection Prevention Analyst

2011 - Present (9 years)

APIC

Chair National Research committee August 2017 - December 2019 (2 years 5 months)

Abington Memorial Hospital 19 years Critical Care Nurse 1997 - April 2016 (19 years)

Infection Preventionist 2006 - 2011 (5 years)

APIC President Phila-DV Chapter 15 2013 - 2014 (1 year)

Education

Abington Memorial Hospital Dixon School of Nursing Diploma, Registered Nursing/Registered Nurse

Gwynedd-Mercy College MSN, Nursing Education

Immaculata University BSN, Nursing Science